<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../../../../schemas/styles/kenya.xsl"?>
<!--Akoma_Ntoso document-->
<akomantoso xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/1.0"
			xmlns:bungeni="http://www.bungeni.org/proprietary" 
			xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
			xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/1.0 ../akomantoso10.xsd">
	<act contains="OriginalVersion">
		<meta>
			<identification source="#bungeni">
				<FRBRWork>
					<this value="/ke/act/1980-01-01/1/main"/>
					<uri value="/ke/act/1980-01-01/1"/>
					<date date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
					<author href="#parliament" as="#author"/>
					<components>
						<component id="wmain" href="#emain" name="main" showAs="Main document"/>
					</components>
				</FRBRWork>
				<FRBRExpression>
					<this value="/ke/act/1980-01-01/1/eng@/main"/>
					<uri value="/ke/act/1980-01-01/1/eng@"/>
					<date date="2007-11-22" name="Generation"/>
					<author href="#bungeni" as="#jurist"/>
					<components>
						<component id="emain" href="#mmain" name="main" showAs="Main document"/>
					</components>
				</FRBRExpression>
				<FRBRManifestation>
					<this value="/ke/act/1980-01-01/1/eng@/main.xml"/>
					<uri value="/ke/act/1980-01-01/1/eng@.akn"/>
					<date date="2007-11-22" name="Generation"/>
					<author href="#bungeni" as="#editor"/>
					<author href="#be" as="#editor"/>
					<components>
						<component id="mmain" href="main.xml" name="main" showAs="Main document"/>
					</components>
				</FRBRManifestation>
			</identification>
			<publication name="" date="1980-01-01" showAs=""/>
			<lifecycle source="#bungeni">
				<event id="e1" date="1980-01-01" source="#ro1" type="Generation"/>
			</lifecycle>
			<references source="#bungeni">
				<Original id="ro1" href="/ke/act/1980-01-01/1/eng@/main" showAs="Original"/>
				<TLCOrganization id="bungeni" href="/ontology/organization/kn/bungeni/kn.bungeni"
					showAs="bungeni"/>
		        <TLCPerson id="be" href="/ontology/person/editors/kn.be" showAs="A Bungeni Editor"/>
				<TLCOrganization id="parliament" href="/ontology/organization/ke/ke.parliament"
					showAs="Parliament of Kenya"/>
				<TLCRole id="editor" href="/ontology/roles/editor" showAs="Editor"/>
				<TLCRole id="jurist" href="/ontology/roles/jurist" showAs="Jurist"/>
				<TLCRole id="author" href="/ontology/roles/author" showAs="Author"/>
			</references>
			<notes source="#au1">
				<note id="n1">
					<p>1. MY ANNOTATION</p>
				</note>
			</notes>
		</meta>
		<preface>
			<p>CHAPTER 376 - <ActTitle id="ActTitle">Wildlife (Conservation and Management)
				Act</ActTitle>
			</p>
		</preface>
		<preamble id="preamble">
			<p>An Act of Parliament to consolidate and amend the law relating to the protection,
				conservation and management of wildlife in Kenya; and for purposes connected there
				with and incidental thereto<eol/>WHEREAS is desirable that the present powers
				relating to the management and conservation of wildlife in Kenya should be
				amalgamated and placed in a consolidated Service of the Government;<eol/>AND WHEREAS
				the prime objective of the Service should be to ensure that wildlife is managed and
				conserved so as to yield to the Nation in general and to individual areas in
				particular, optimum returns in terms of cultural, aesthetic and scientific gains as
				well as such economic gains as are incidental to proper wildlife management and
				conservation and which may be secured without prejudice to such proper management
				and conservation;<eol/>AND WHEREAS it is necessary, for the achievement of that
				objective, that full account should be taken of the varied forms of land use and the
				inter-relationship between wildlife conservation and management and other forms of
				land use:<eol/>Now THEREFORE BE IT ENACTED by the Parliament of Kenya, as follows:
			-</p>
		</preamble>
		<body>
			<part id="prtI">
				<heading>PART I-PRELIMINARY</heading>
				<section id="sec1">
					<heading>Short title</heading>
					<subsection id="sec1-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>1. This <ref id="ref64" href="/ke/act/1980-01-01/1/main">Act</ref>
								may be cited as the Wildlife (Conservation and Management)
									Act<noteref href="#n1" num="1"/>.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec2">
					<heading>Interpretation.</heading>
					<subsection id="sec2-sub1">
						<sidenote>11 of 1983, Sch., 16 of 1989, s.2, 2 of 2002, Sch. Cap. 385</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>2. In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires-
								<eol/>"aircraft" means any type of aeroplane, airship, balloon or
								kite, whether captive, navigable or free, and whether controlled or
								directed by human agency or not: <eol/>"animal" means any animal or
								the young or egg thereof, but does not include a human being or any
								animal which is commonly considered to be a domestic animal or the
								young or egg thereof;<eol/>"appointed day" means the day fixed under
								subsection (2);<eol/>"competent authority" means- <eol/>(a) in
								relation to Government land, the Minister for the time being
								responsible for matters relating to land; <eol/>(b) in relation to
								Trust land, the county council in which the land is vested;
								<eol/>(c) in relation to any other land, the owner thereof or the
								person for the time being entitled to the rents and profits thereof;
								<eol/>"dangerous animal" means an elephant, a rhinoceros, a
								hippopotamus, a buffalo, a lion or a leopard; <eol/>"dealer" means
								any person who, in the ordinary course of any business or trade
								carried on by him, whether on his own behalf or on behalf of any
								other person- <eol/>(a) sells, purchases, barters or otherwise in
								any manner deals with any trophy; or <eol/>(b) cuts, carves,
								polishes, preserves, cleans, mounts or otherwise prepares any
								trophy;<eol/>"Director" means the Director of the Service appointed
								under <ref id="ref2" href="#sec3.c">section 3C</ref>; <eol/>"export"
								includes re-export; <eol/>"forest officer" has the meaning assigned
								to it by the Forests Act; <eol/>"forfeiture offence" means an
								offence which is so designated by any of the provisions of this Act
								creating offences; <eol/>"former Trustees" means the Trustees of the
								National Parks of Kenya established by the National Parks of Kenya
								Act (now repealed); <eol/>"game animal" means an animal specified in
								the First Schedule; <eol/>"game bird" means a bird specified in the
								Second Schedule; <eol/>"game licence" means a licence issued under
									<ref id="ref3" href="#sec23">section 23</ref>; <eol/>"Government
								trophy" means a trophy declared to be a Government trophy by section
								39; "hunt" includes the doing of any act immediately directed at the
								killing, wounding, injuring or capture of any animal, and the taking
								or wilful molestation of any nest or eggs; <eol/>"land" includes
								land covered by sea or other water; <eol/>"licensing officer", in
								respect of any of the provisions of this Act, means a person
								appointed by the Minister, by notice in the Gazette, to be a
								licensing officer for the purposes of that provision; <eol/>"local
								sanctuary" means an area of land declared to be a local sanctuary by
								or under <ref id="ref4" href="#sec19">section 19</ref>; <eol/>"meat"
								means the fat, blood, flesh or tissue of any game animal, game bird
								or protected species, whether fresh or dried, pickled or otherwise
								preserved or processed; <eol/>"Minister" means the Minister for the
								time being responsible for matters relating to wildlife;<eol/>"motor
								vehicle" includes a vehicle of the type commonly known as a
								"hovercraft"; <eol/>"National Park" means any area of land declared
								to be a National Park by or under <ref id="ref5" href="#sec6"
									>section 6</ref>; <eol/>"National Reserve" means any area of
								land declared to be a National Reserve by or under <ref id="ref6"
									href="#sec18">section 18</ref>; <eol/>"owner", in relation to
								private land, includes a lesee or a mortgagee in possession, and any
								person authorized by an owner, lessee or mortgagee in possession to
								act on his behalf in his absence, and group representatives
								incorporated under the Land (Group Representatives) Act;
								<eol/>"private land" means any land- <eol/>(a) which is held under a
								conveyance, lease or licence (other than a temporary occupation
								licence under the Government Lands Act) from the Government or a
								county council; or <eol/>(b) which has been recorded as being in the
								ownership of any person or group of persons under any written law
								relating to the adjudication or recording of such ownership;
								<eol/>"professional hunter" means the holder of a valid licence
								issued under <ref id="ref7" href="#sec27">section 27</ref>;
								<eol/>"protected animal" means an animal, or an animal of a
								species,<eol/>sub-species or group, specified in the Third Schedule;
								<eol/>"protection area" means an area declared to be a protection
								area under <ref id="ref8" href="#sec15">section 15</ref>;
								<eol/>"rules" means any rules, regulations or by-laws made under
								this Act; <eol/>"senior officer" means a warden, a forest officer of
								or above the rank of assistant conservator of forests, or a police
								officer of or above the rank of Assistant Inspector;<eol/>"Service"
								means the Kenya Wildlife Service established under section
								3.<eol/>"subordinate officer" means any authorized officer who is
								not a senior officer; <eol/>"trophy" means any protected animal,
								game animal, or game bird alive or dead, and any bone, claw, egg,
								feather, hair, hoof, skin, tooth, tusk or other durable portion
								whatsoever of that animal or bird or fish or other aquatic life
								whether processed, added to or changed by the work of man or not,
								which is recognizable as such a durable portion; <eol/>"Trustees"
								means the Board of Trustees of the Trust;<eol/>"warden" means a
								member of the Service above the rank of ranger;</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
			</part>
			<part id="prtII">
				<heading>PART II - ADMINISTRATION</heading>
				<section id="sec3">
					<heading>Establishment of the Service.</heading>
					<subsection id="sec3-sub1">
						<sidenote>16 of 1989, s.3. Cap 287</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>3. (1) There is hereby established a uniformed and disciplined
								service to be known as the Kenya Wildlife Service.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec3-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The Kenya Wildlife Service shall be a body corporate with perpetual
								succession and a common seal and shall have power to sue and be sued
								in its corporate name and to acquire, hold and dispose of immovable
								property for the purposes of the service and this Act.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec3-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The headquarters of the service shall be situated in Nairobi.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec3-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The service shall be the successor to the Wildlife Fund Trustees
								established under section 489 now repaealed and, subject too this
								Act all rights, duties and obligations, assets and liabilities shall
								be automatically an duly transferred to the Service and any
								reference to the Wildlife Fund Trustees in any written law or in any
								contract or document shall for all purposes be deemed to be a
								reference of the Service established under <ref id="ref9"
									href="#sec3-sub1">subsection (1)</ref>.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec4">
					<heading>Honorary wardens</heading>
					<subsection id="sec4-sub1">
						<sidenote>A16/89.</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>4.(1) The Director may, with the prior approval of the Minister,
								appoint fit and proper persons to be honorary wardens for the
								purpose of assisting in the carrying into effect of the provisions
								of this Act.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec4-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The appointment of an honorary game warden-</p>
							<list id="sec4-sub2-lst1">
								<item id="sec4-sub2-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>shall be notified in the Gazette;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec4-sub2-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>shall be effective unless sooner revoked by the Director, for
										a period of three years; and</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec4-sub2-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>may be made subject to any conditions which the Director may
										think fit to impose.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec5">
					<heading>Delegation, etc., of functions</heading>
					<subsection id="sec5-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>5.(1) The Director may delegate or assign any of his functions under
								this Act- </p>
							<list id="sec5-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec5-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>to any member of the Service; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec5-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>to any officer of the Forest Department; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec5-sub1-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>to any officer of the Fisheries Department; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec5-sub1-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>to any public officer, approved by the Minister.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec5-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any delegation or assignment under this section shall be by notice in
								the Gazette and may have effect throughout Kenya or in such area
								only as may be specified in the notice.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
			</part>
			<part id="prtIII">
				<heading>PART III - NATIONAL PARKS, NATIONAL RESERVES AND LOCAL SANCTUARIES</heading>
				<section id="sec6">
					<heading>Declaration of National Parks</heading>
					<subsection id="sec6-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>6. (1) The Minister, after consultation with the competent authority,
								may by order declare any area of land to be a National Park:
								<eol/>Provided that, where the competent authority does not consent
								to the declaration, no order shall be made unless- </p>
							<list id="sec6-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec6-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>the National Assembly has, by resolution, approved a draft of
										the order, whether with or without modification; and</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec6-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>in the case of Trust land, the area concerned has first been
										set apart in accordance with section 118 of the
										Constitution; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec6-sub1-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>in the case of private land, the area concerned has first
										been acquired under the Land Acquisition Act.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec6-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>All National Parks declared to be such under the National Parks of
								Kenya Act and existing immediately before the appointed day are
								declared to be National Parks for all the purposes of this Act, and
								the names and boundaries of such National Parks, unless and until
								they are amended under this Act, shall be those existing on the
								appointed day.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec6-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>All National Parks staff existing immediately before the appointed
								day, unless and until replaced under this Act, shall be the staff of
								the Government on the appointed day.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec7">
					<heading>Cessation of area as a National Park, National Reserve or local
						sanctuary</heading>
					<subsection id="sec7-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>7. (1) Subject to <ref id="ref15" href="#sec7-sub2">subsection
								(2)</ref>, the Minister, after consultation with the competent
								authority, may by order declare that any National Park, National
								Reserve, local sanctuary or a specified part thereof, shall cease to
								be a National Park, National Reserve or local sanctuary.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec7-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>No order shall be made under subsection (1) unless-</p>
							<list id="sec7-sub2-lst1">
								<item id="sec7-sub2-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>a notice of the intention to make the order, with details
										thereof, and inviting objections thereto within a period of
										not more than 60 days, has been published in the Gazette and
										in at least one newspaper circulating throughout Kenya;
									and</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec7-sub2-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>not earlier than sixty days after the last date of such
										publication a draft of the order has been laid before the
										National Assembly and the National Assembly has by
										resolution approved the order.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec8">
					<heading>Amendment of boundaries</heading>
					<subsection id="sec8-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>8. Subject to sections 6 and 7, the Minister may, by order- </p>
							<list id="sec8-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec8-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>assign a name to a National Park or amend any such name;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec8-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>define the boundaries of a National Park, or alter the same
										whether by adding to or subtracting from the area thereof or
										otherwise;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec8-sub1-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>amalgamate two or more National Parks into one National
									Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec8-sub1-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>divide any National Park into two or more National Parks;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec8-sub1-itme">
									<num>(e)</num>
									<p>transfer any part of a National Park to another National
										Park.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec9">
					<heading>Management of National Parks</heading>
					<subsection id="sec9-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>9.(1) The Director shall, through the member of the Service, control,
								manage and maintain all National Parks.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec9-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Within a National Park the Director may-</p>
							<list id="sec9-sub2-lst1">
								<item id="sec9-sub2-itmi">
									<num>(i)</num>
									<p>reserve or set aside any portion of the Park as a breeding
										place for animals or as nurseries for vegetation;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec9-sub2-itmii">
									<num>(ii)</num>
									<p>authorize the construction of such roads, bridges, air
										fields, buildings and fences, the provision of such water
										supplies, and the carrying out of such other works, as may
										be necessary for the purposes of the Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec9-sub2-itmiii">
									<num>(iii)</num>
									<p>with the approval of the Minister, let sites for the erection
										of hotels, or other accommodation for visitors to the
									Park:</p>
								</item>
							</list>
							<p>Provided that nothing in any document connected with the letting
								shall be construed as in any manner abridging the overall control of
								the Park by the Service, or as preventing the Director from giving
								directions as to the manner in which the premises concerned shall be
								managed in the interests of the matters set forth in <ref id="ref16"
									href="#sec9-sub2-itmii">paragraph (i)</ref>.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec10">
					<heading>Restriction on prospecting and mining</heading>
					<subsection id="sec10-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>10. (1) Subject to any rights lawfully acquired before the relevant
								date, and notwithstanding anything contained in any other written
								law, no person shall search for, attempt to win or win any minerals
								in, or remove any minerals from, a National Park except with the
								written consent of the Minister given after consultation with the
								Minister for the time being responsible for mines, and in accordance
								with any conditions which the Minister may impose in relation to
								that consent.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec10-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who is aggrieved by the giving or withholding of consent
								by the Minister and any conditions imposed in connexion therewith
								may, within fourteen days of the Minister's decision, appeal to the
								High Court.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec10-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The Minister may, in consultation with the Minister for the time
								being responsible for mines, by notice in the Gazette, prescribe
								fees chargeable in respect of any consent given under this
							section.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec10-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The giving of a consent under this section shall not be construed as
								in any manner exempting any person from complying with the
								provisions of any other written law relating to the searching for,
								or the mining or winning of, minerals.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec10-sub5">
						<num>(5)</num>
						<content>
							<p>For the purposes of <ref id="ref17" href="#sec10-sub1">subsection
								(1)</ref>, "relevant date" means-</p>
							<list id="sec10-sub5-lst1">
								<item id="sec10-sub5-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>in respect of a National Park declared by <ref id="ref18"
											href="#sec6-sub2">subsection (2) of section 6</ref> to
										be a National Park, the appointed day; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec10-sub5-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>in respect of any area declared under <ref id="ref19"
											href="#sec6-sub1">subsection (1) of section 6</ref> to
										be a National Park, the date upon which the relevant order
										under that subsection comes into operation.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec10-sub6">
						<num>(6)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who contravenes <ref id="ref20" href="#sec10-sub1"
									>subsection (1)</ref>, or who fails to comply with any
								conditions imposed by the Minister under that subsection, shall be
								guilty of a forfeiture offence and shall be liable to a fine of not
								less than twenty thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a period
								of not less than three years, or to both in addition to any penalty
								for forfeiture offences.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec11">
					<heading>Restriction on commercial film making</heading>
					<subsection id="sec11-sub1">
						<sidenote>Cap. 222.</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>11.(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in the Films and Stage
								Plays Act, no person shall in a National Park make any cinematograph
								film for sale or other commercial use unless the filming licence
								issued under that Act has been produced to the Director and the
								Director has, upon payment of the prescribed fee, given his written
								authorization, subject to such conditions as he may think necessary,
								to the making of the film.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec11-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who contravenes <ref id="ref21" href="#sec11-sub1"
									>subsection (1)</ref>, or who fails to comply with any
								conditions imposed in connexion with any authorization under this
								section, shall be guilty of a forfeiture offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec12">
					<heading>Flying restrictions in respect of National Parks</heading>
					<subsection id="sec12-sub1">
						<sidenote>6 of 1976, Sch. </sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>12. (1) Except as may be necessitated by sudden emergency endangering
								the safety of any aircraft, the proof of which shall lie on the
								pilot thereof, no aircraft- </p>
							<list id="sec12-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec12-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>shall be landed in a National Park otherwise than at a
										recognized airfield and in accordance with the rules;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec12-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>except for the purpose of landing at or taking off from a
										recognized airfield, shall be flown at a height of less than
										one thousand five hundred feet over a National Park unless
										the written authorization of the Minister, which may be
										given subject to such conditions as the Minister may think
										fit to impose, has previously been obtained.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec12-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The pilot of an aircraft who contravenes the provisions of this
								section, or fails to comply with any conditions attached to an
								authorization by the Minister, shall be guilty of an offence and
								liable to a fine not exceeding ten thousand shillings or to
								imprisonment for a term not exceeding twelve months or to both:
								<eol/>Provided that nothing in this subsection shall apply to the
								operation of any aircraft which is, at the time of the
								contravention, being used for any purpose of the Service.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec13">
					<heading>General offences in National Parks</heading>
					<subsection id="sec13-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>13. (1) Any person who, not being a member of the Service acting in
								the course of his duties as such, hunts any animal in a National
								Park shall be guilty of a forfeiture offence and liable to a fine of
								not less than five thousand shillings and not more than twenty
								thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a term which shall not be
								less than six months and not more than three years, with or without
								corporal punishment or to both.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec13-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who, without authorization conveys into a National Park,
								or being within the area thereof, is in possession of, any weapon,
								ammunition, explosive, trap or poison, shall be guilty of a
								forfeiture offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec13-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who, without authorization-</p>
							<list id="sec13-sub3-lst1">
								<item id="sec13-sub3-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>enters or resides in a National Park otherwise than in the
										course of his duty as a public officer or as a person
										lawfully employed in the Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec13-sub3-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>cuts, injures or sets fire to any vegetation in a National
										Park, or allows any fire lighted by himself or his servants
										to enter a National Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec13-sub3-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>collects or attempts to collect any honey or beeswax or hangs
										on any tree or elsewhere any honey barrel or other
										receptacle for the purpose of collecting honey or beeswax,
										in a National Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec13-sub3-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>willfully damages any object of geological, prehistoric,
										archaeological, historic, marine or other scientific
										interest within a National Park, or knowingly removes or
										attempts to remove any such object or any portion thereof
										from a National Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec13-sub3-itme">
									<num>(e)</num>
									<p>is, without lawful excuse in possession of any animal or
										trophy within or without a National Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec13-sub3-itmf">
									<num>(f)</num>
									<p>knowingly introduces any animal or domestic animal or
										vegetation into a National Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec13-sub3-itmg">
									<num>(g)</num>
									<p>deliberately disturbs or stampedes any animal in a National
										Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec13-sub3-itmh">
									<num>(h)</num>
									<p>wilfully damages any structure lawfully placed in a National
										Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec13-sub3-itmi">
									<num>(i)</num>
									<p>clears, cultivates or breaks up for cultivation any land in a
										National Park; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec13-sub3-itmj">
									<num>(j)</num>
									<p>catches or attempts to catch any fish in a National Park,</p>
								</item>
							</list>
							<p>shall be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding ten
								thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding one
								year or to both. </p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec13-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>For the purposes of this section, an act shall be deemed to be done
								with authorization if, but only if, it-</p>
							<list id="sec13-sub4-lst1">
								<item id="sec13-sub4-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>is authorized by the rules; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec13-sub4-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>is done with the written permission of an officer of the
										Service; and</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec13-sub4-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>the provisions of the rules, or any conditions imposed upon
										such permission by the officer concerned, are fully complied
										with.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec14">
					<heading>Animal not to be followed into national park</heading>
					<subsection id="sec14-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>14.(1) Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, no person
								shall follow any wounded animal into a National Park, and where,
								under that provision, a person has in other circumstances a duty to
								follow or kill, or to make a report relating to a wounded animal he
								shall, at the earliest practicable moment, make a report to an
								officer of the Service as to all the circumstances of the case.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec14-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who contravenes this section shall be guilty of an offence
								and liable to a fine not exceeding five thousand shillings or to
								imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months or to both.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec15">
					<heading>Protection areas</heading>
					<subsection id="sec15-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>15.(1) Where the Minister, after consultation with the competent
								authority, is satisfied that it is necessary, for ensuring the
								security of the animal or vegetable life in a National Park or in a
								National Reserve or in a local sanctuary or for preserving the
								habitat and ecology thereof, to prohibit, restrict or regulate any
								particular acts in any area adjacent to the Park, National Reserve
								or local sanctuary he may, by notice in the Gazette, declare the
								area to be a protection area and may, by the same or a subsequent
								notice, specify the acts which are prohibited or restricted or
								regulated and the extent or manner of the restriction or
							regulation.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec15-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who, in a protection area, does any act in contravention
								of a notice under <ref id="ref22" href="#sec15-sub1">subsection
								(1)</ref> relating to that area shall be guilty of an offence and
								liable to a fine not exceeding five thousand shillings or to
								imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months or to both.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec16">
					<heading>National Park Regulations</heading>
					<subsection id="sec16-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>16. (1) The Minister may make regulations for any or all of the
								following matters- </p>
							<list id="sec16-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec16-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>the form in, and the conditions subject to which permission
										to enter a National Park may be granted or withdrawn, and
										the periods or times during which a National Park or any
										portion thereof shall be open to the public;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec16-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>the fees to be paid for permission to enter or reside in a
										National Park, for the admission of vehicles, or for the use
										of any amenities provided by the Service in a National
									Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec16-sub1-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>the conditions under, and the extent to, which any of the
										acts mentioned in <ref id="ref23" href="#sec16-sub2"
											>subsection (2)</ref> or <ref id="ref24"
											href="#sec16-sub3">subsection (3)</ref> of section 13
										may be lawfully performed and the fees to be paid in respect
										of such performance;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec16-sub1-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>the conditions under which the services or attendance of
										members of the Service, or of any other person licensed in
										that behalf by the Director, may be obtained in a National
										Park, and the fees to be paid in respect thereof;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec16-sub1-itme">
									<num>(e)</num>
									<p>the regulation of landing of aircraft in, and of traffic in
										or over, a National Park, the carriage of goods and
										passengers in a National Park, the points by which a person
										may enter, and the routes to be followed in or through, a
										National Park;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec16-sub1-itmf">
									<num>(f)</num>
									<p>generally for the efficient control and management of a
										National Park and the efficient performance of the duties of
										the Service therein.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec16-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Regulations under this section may be made applicable to all or any
								specified National Parks, and different regulations may be made in
								respect of different National Parks.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec16-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Regulations under this section may provide, in respect of any
								contravention thereof, penalties not exceeding a fine of six
								thousand shillings or imprisonment for a term not exceeding six
								months.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec17">
					<heading>Impounding of domestic animals</heading>
					<subsection id="sec17-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>17. Any domestic animal found in a National Park may be impounded by
								an Officer of the Service and the owner thereof shall prove
								ownership before delivery.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec18">
					<heading>National Reserves</heading>
					<subsection id="sec18-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>18. (1) With the agreement of the competent authority, the Minister
								may, by notice in the Gazette, declare any area of land to be a
								National Reserve.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec18-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>An agreement between the Minister and a competent authority under
									<ref id="ref25" href="#sec18-sub1">subsection (1)</ref> may
								include agreement as to restrictions or conditions relating to the
								provisions of this Part which shall apply to the area concerned, and
								any such restrictions or conditions shall be specified by the
								Minister in the notice declaring the area to be a National
							Reserve.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec18-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The provisions of this Part shall apply to a National Reserve as they
								apply to a National Park except in so far as-</p>
							<list id="sec18-sub3-lst1">
								<item id="sec18-sub3-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>they are modified or excluded by any such conditions or
										restrictions as are mentioned in <ref id="ref26"
											href="#sec18-sub2">subsection (2)</ref>; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec18-sub3-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>they are further modified or excluded as the Minister may, by
										the notice declaring the area to be a National Reserve or by
										a subsequent notice in the Gazette, otherwise direct.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec18-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any areas which, immediately before the appointed day, were
								administered by the former Trustees as national reserves shall on
								that day become National Reserves for the purposes of this Act, and
								the powers, duties and functions which immediately before the
								appointed day were exercisable by the former Trustees in any such
								area shall thereafter be exercisable by the Director in so far as
								they conform to the provisions of this Part.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec18-sub5">
						<num>(5)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Notwithstanding any law to the contrary, no person shall purport to
								establish any game reserve or National Reserve except with the
								approval of the Minister, and any such approval-</p>
							<list id="sec18-sub5-lst1">
								<item id="sec18-sub5-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>may be made subject to such conditions and restrictions,
										including conditions relating to the application of this
										Part to such reserve, as the Minister may, after
										consultations with the competent authority impose;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec18-sub5-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>shall be published in the Gazette.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec18-sub6">
						<num>(6)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any area which, immediately before the appointed day, was
								administered by a local authority as a game reserve shall become a
								National Reserve and shall continue to be so administered until the
								Minister, after consultations with the competent authority, by
								notice in the Gazette, otherwise directs either generally or in
								relation to any specified area.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec19">
					<heading>Local sanctuaries.</heading>
					<subsection id="sec19-sub1">
						<sidenote>Cap.376 (1962)</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>19.(1) The Minister may, after consultation with the competent
								authority, by notice in the Gazette, declare that any specified area
								shall be a local sanctuary wherein any animal specified in the same
								or a later notice shall not be hunted.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec19-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The area of a local sanctuary shall not exceed two thousand six
								hundred hectares.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec19-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>All local sanctuaries declared to be such under the Wild Animals
								Protection Act (now repealed) and existing immediately before the
								appointed day are declared to be local sanctuaries for all the
								purposes of this Act.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec19-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who in a local sanctuary hunts any animal which is
								specified in respect of that sanctuary under <ref id="ref27"
									href="#sec19-sub1">subsection (1)</ref> shall be guilty of a
								forfeiture offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec20">
					<heading>Agreements by Director</heading>
					<subsection id="sec20-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>20.(1) The Director may enter into any agreement with a competent
								authority which the Director may consider necessary for the purpose
								of ensuring that animal migration patterns essential to the
								continued viability of a National Park or National Reserve are
								maintained.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec20-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>An agreement under this section may, with the approval of the
								Minister, provide for compensation to be payable to the competent
								authority concerned in respect of rights forgone or of damage caused
								by animals.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
			</part>
			<part id="prtIV">
				<heading>PART IV - CONTROL OF HUNTING</heading>
				<section id="sec21">
					<heading>Powers of honorary wardens</heading>
					<subsection id="sec21-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>21. An honorary warden appointed under <ref id="ref28"
									href="#sec19-sub4">section 4</ref> shall, for all the purposes
								of this Part, be deemed to be a warden.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec22">
					<heading>Prohibition of unlicensed hunting, etc.  </heading>
					<subsection id="sec22-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>22. (1) Except as otherwise expressly provided by this Act or the
								rules any person who- </p>
							<list id="sec22-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec22-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>hunts any protected animal; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec22-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>hunts any animal otherwise than as the holder of, and in
										accordance with any conditions attaching to, a game licence
										authorizing him to hunt that animal, shall be guilty of a
										forfeiture offence.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec22-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Except as otherwise provided by this Act or the rules, any person who
								hunts any game bird otherwise than as the holder of, and in
								accordance with any conditions attaching to, a game licence
								authorizing him to hunt such bird shall be guilty of an offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec23">
					<heading>General provisions as to game licences</heading>
					<subsection id="sec23-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>23.(1) Subject to subsection (4) of section 3, a licensing officer
								may issue in accordance with the rules a game licence in a
								prescribed form.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec23-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Game licences shall, subject to <ref id="ref29" href="#prtIII">Part
									III</ref>, authorize the hunting of such game animals or game
								birds, in such areas, for such periods and subject to such
								conditions as may be prescribed, and the prescribed fees shall be
								payable in respect of the issue thereof.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec23-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, no game licence
								shall authorize the holder thereof to hunt any game animal unless-</p>
							<list id="sec23-sub3-lst1">
								<item id="sec23-sub3-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>he is a professional hunter; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec23-sub3-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>he is accompanied at the time of hunting by a professional
										hunter; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec23-sub3-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>his licence is endorsed by the Director, after such inquiry
										or test as to competence as the Director may think fit, to
										the effect that the holder may, subject to any conditions
										which the Director may consider necessary, hunt
										unaccompanied by a professional hunter either generally or
										in respect of the animal actually hunted.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec24">
					<heading>General provisions as to game licences</heading>
					<subsection id="sec24-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>24.(1) For the purpose of computing the number of game animals or
								game birds which may be hunted under a game licence, all animals or
								birds which are killed, wounded or captured shall be taken into
								account.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec24-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Every holder of a game licence shall carry the licence with him at
								all times when engaged upon any of the activities authorized by the
								licence, and any person who fails to comply with this subsection
								shall be guilty of an offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec24-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Subject to the provisions of this Act relating to the cancellation of
								licences, a game licence shall be valid for the period specified in
								the licence:<eol/>Provided that a game licence shall cease to be
								valid as soon as all the animals the hunting of which is authorized
								by the licence have been killed, wounded or captured.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec25">
					<heading>Game registers </heading>
					<subsection id="sec25-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>25. (1) Every holder of a game licence shall keep a register in the
								prescribed form of the prescribed particulars of every game animal
								killed, wounded or captured by him, or deemed by any provision of
								this Act to have been killed, wounded or captured by him.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec25-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Every professional hunter shall keep a register in such form, and
								containing such particulars, as the Director may require at the time
								that the professional hunter's licence is issued.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec25-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>So far as is practicable, every register kept under this section
								shall have the registrable particulars entered therein at the
								conclusion of each day's hunting.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec25-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>A person required to keep a register under this section shall-</p>
							<list id="sec25-sub4-lst1">
								<item id="sec25-sub4-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>produce the register at any reasonable time upon being
										requested to do so by an authorized officer;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec25-sub4-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>produce the register to a warden within seven days after the
										date upon which any game licence held by him ceases to be
										valid under <ref id="ref30" href="#sec24-sub4">subsection
											(4) of section 24</ref>;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec25-sub4-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>furnish to the Director within twenty-one days after such
										date a copy of the register.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec25-sub5">
						<num>(5)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who, being required by this section to keep a register-</p>
							<list id="sec25-sub5-lst1">
								<item id="sec25-sub5-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>fails so to do;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec25-sub5-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>makes, or is privy to the making of, any false entry in such
										register;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec25-sub5-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>fails to record in the register any particulars which are
										required to be so recorded; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec25-sub5-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>fails to produce the register, or to furnish a copy thereof,
										when required by <ref id="ref31" href="#sec25-sub4"
											>subsection (4)</ref> so to do, shall be guilty of an
										offence, and liable to a fine not exceeding five thousand
										shillings or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six
										months or to both.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec26">
					<heading>Special authorization to hunt</heading>
					<subsection id="sec26-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>26. (1) Where the Director is satisfied that it is desirable so to do
								for scientific purposes, or by reason of any circumstances of an
								unusual or emergency nature, he may, with the prior approval of the
								Minister in each case, issue a special authorization to hunt any
								animal in any specified area other than a National Park.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec26-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>An authorization issued under this section-</p>
							<list id="sec26-sub2-lst1">
								<item id="sec26-sub2-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>shall be subject to such conditions as the Director may deem
										it necessary or desirable to impose thereon;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec26-sub2-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>shall, except as may be expressly provided by any such
										condition, be deemed to be a game licence for all the
										purposes of this Act; and</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec26-sub2-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>shall be subject to the payment of such fee as the Minister
										may, on granting his approval thereof, direct.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec27">
					<heading>Professional hunters</heading>
					<subsection id="sec27-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>27.(1) Any person who, not being the holder of a professional
								hunter's licence issued under this section- </p>
							<list id="sec27-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec27-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>carries on the business of a professional hunter, or
										advertises himself or solicits custom in connexion with such
										business; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec27-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>for hire or reward with the intention of making profit,
										assists any person to hunt any game animal or game bird,
										shall be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not
										exceeding ten thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a
										period not exceeding three years or to both:</p>
								</item>
							</list>
							<p>Provided that paragraph(b)shall not apply to any person employed
								solely as a tracker, gun-bearer or beater. </p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec27-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The Director may issue a professional hunter's licence to any person
								who is able to satisfy the Director that by reason of his competence
								with firearms, knowledge of game animals and of the written law
								pertaining thereto, and of any other matters which the Director may
								consider relevant, he is a fit and proper person to carry on the
								business of a professional hunter: <eol/>Provided that where a
								person seeks a professional hunter's licence in continuation of one
								previously held by him he shall, in the absence of any evidence to
								the contrary, be deemed to be such a fit and proper person.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec27-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>There shall be paid in respect of the issue of a professional
								hunter's licence such fee as may be prescribed and, subject to the
								provisions of this section, every such licence shall be valid for
								the period of twelve months following the date of issue thereof.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec27-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>If the holder of a professional hunter's licence is convicted of any
								offence under this Act or the rules-</p>
							<list id="sec27-sub4-lst1">
								<item id="sec27-sub4-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>he shall, within fourteen days after the date of his
										conviction, surrender his licence to the Director for
										cancellation; and</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec27-sub4-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>he shall not be eligible to be issued with another licence
										for such period as the Director may determine having regard
										to the circumstances of the case,</p>
								</item>
							</list>
							<p>and any person who fails to surrender his licence accordingly shall
								be guilty of an offence. </p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec27-sub5">
						<num>(5)</num>
						<content>
							<p>A professional hunter's licence shall not authorize the hunting of
								any animal by the holder thereof except in so far as may be
								necessary in his own defence or in the defence of any other person
								or to prevent the escape of a wounded animal: <eol/>Provided that
								where an animal so killed was wounded by the holder of a game
								licence employing the professional hunter it shall, for all the
								purposes of this Act, be deemed to have been killed by such
							holder.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec27-sub6">
						<num>(6)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Where any person who commits an offence against this Act or the rules
								is accompanied by a professional hunter, employed by him, at the
								time that the offence is committed, the professional hunter shall,
								unless he establishes to the satisfaction of the court that he used
								all due diligence to prevent the commission of the offence and was
								unable to prevent the commission thereof, be guilty of the like
								offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec28">
					<heading>Cancellation, etc., of licences</heading>
					<subsection id="sec28-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>28.(1) The Director may, without assigning any reason therefor,
								suspend or cancel any licence or authorization issued under this
								Part, and in any such case a proportionate part of the fee paid for
								the licence may be refunded to the person to whom it was issued.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec28-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any officer authorized under this Part to issue any licence or
								authorization may, if he thinks fit and without assigning any reason
								therefor, refuse to issue the licence or authorization.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec29">
					<heading>Hunting on private land</heading>
					<subsection id="sec29-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>29.(1) No game licence shall authorize hunting on any private land
								unless it is expressed so to do by endorsement specifying the land
								concerned, made by a licensing officer, and no such endorsement
								shall be made unless- </p>
							<list id="sec29-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec29-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>the holder of the licence is the owner of the land concerned;
										or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec29-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>the person applying for the endorsement produces to the
										licensing officer the written consent of the owner of the
										land thereto; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec29-sub1-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>the land concerned is registered under <ref id="ref32"
											href="#sec29-sub2">subsection (2)</ref>.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec29-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Where the owner of private land desires to afford facilities for the
								hunting of game animals or game birds on the land, he may register
								the land, in such manner and on furnishing such particulars as may
								be prescribed, with the Director or with such officer of the Service
								as the Director may, by notice in the Gazette, appoint for that
								purpose, and in any such case-</p>
							<list id="sec29-sub2-lst1">
								<item id="sec29-sub2-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>the registration may be effected in respect of the whole of
										the land of such owner or of such portion thereof as the
										owner may specify;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec29-sub2-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>the registration may be made subject to such conditions as to
										the giving of notice to the owner or his representative of
										intention to hunt, or as to the types of animals which may
										be hunted, as the owner may specify, and any endorsement
										under this section in respect of the land shall include a
										reference to such conditions;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec29-sub2-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>there shall be paid to the registered owner such fees,
										whether calculated as a proportion of the fees paid in
										respect of licences endorsed as valid in respect of the land
										of the owner or otherwise, as may be prescribed.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec30">
					<heading>Protection of human life</heading>
					<subsection id="sec30-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>30.(1) Nothing in this Act shall make it an offence for any person to
								kill or injure by any means any animal in immediate defence of human
								life; but the exemption provided by this subsection shall not apply
								where such killing or injuring is done by any person who, at the
								time thereof, was committing an offence under this Act or is done
								under circumstances amounting to deliberate provocation or
								enticement of the animal by or with the knowledge of that
							person.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec30-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Where a protected animal or game animal is killed in immediate
								defence of human life the person killing the animal shall make a
								report of the fact at the earliest practicable moment to an officer
								of the Service.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec31">
					<heading>Protection of property</heading>
					<subsection id="sec31-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>31. Notwithstanding anything to the contrary in this Act any occupier
								of land or his servant or any owner of crops or stock or his
								servant, may, if necessary for the protection of his land, crops or
								stock, kill any game animal which is causing material damage or loss
								to his land or to any crop or stock thereon.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec32">
					<heading>Wounded animals</heading>
					<subsection id="sec32-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>32. (1) Where any person, in any circumstances whatsoever, wounds a
								protected animal or game animal he and any professional hunter
								accompanying him shall make every endeavour to kill or recover the
								animal at the earliest opportunity.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec32-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Where an animal mentioned in <ref id="ref33" href="#sec32-sub1"
									>subsection (1)</ref> is not killed or recovered within
								twenty-four hours after the wounding thereof the person by whom the
								animal is wounded shall forthwith make a report of the facts to an
								officer of the Service, who shall take such action upon such report
								as he may consider necessary.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec32-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who fails to comply with the provisions of this section
								shall be guilty of an offence and liable-</p>
							<list id="sec32-sub3-lst1">
								<item id="sec32-sub3-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>if the animal wounded is a dangerous animal, to a fine not
										exceeding ten thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a
										term not exceeding two years or to both;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec32-sub3-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>in any other case, to a fine not exceeding two thousand
										shillings or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding twelve
										months or to both.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec33">
					<heading>Causing suffering</heading>
					<subsection id="sec33-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>33.Any person who- </p>
							<list id="sec33-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec33-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>in any circumstances whatsoever, causes unnecessary or undue
										suffering to a protected animal or game animal; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec33-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>without the permission of a warden, is in possession of or
										has in his control or keeping, any such animal which has
										been maimed or mutilated,</p>
								</item>
							</list>
							<p>shall be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding five
								thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding
								eighteen months or to both.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec34">
					<heading>Unlawful methods of hunting</heading>
					<subsection id="sec34-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>34.(1) No person shall- </p>
							<list id="sec34-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec34-sub1-itma">
									<p>(a) sell, buy, use or have in his possession any gin or
										similar trap having a jaw length of four inches or more, or
										any snare or similar contrivance made of wire;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec34-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>for the purpose of or in connexion with hunting or assisting
										in hunting any animal, cause any fire or surround any animal
										with fire, or make, use or have in his possession any of the
										following things-</p>
									<list id="sec34-sub1-itmb-lst1">
										<item id="sec34-sub1-itmb-itmi">
											<num>(i)</num>
											<p>any firearm capable of firing more than one missile
												as a result of one pressure of the trigger or of
												reloading itself without further action by the
												operator;</p>
										</item>
										<item id="sec34-sub1-itmb-itmii">
											<num>(ii)</num>
											<p>any explosive, other than the propellant charge in
												firearms cartridges, or any missile containing
												explosive;</p>
										</item>
										<item id="sec34-sub1-itmb-itmiii">
											<num>(iii)</num>
											<p>any fixed stake or similar sharp instrument;</p>
										</item>
										<item id="sec34-sub1-itmb-itmiv">
											<num>(iv)</num>
											<p>any set-gun, pitfall, game-pit, trench or similar
												excavation;</p>
										</item>
										<item id="sec34-sub1-itmb-itmv">
											<num>(v)</num>
											<p>any net, fence or enclosure;</p>
										</item>
										<item id="sec34-sub1-itmb-itmvi">
											<num>(vi)</num>
											<p>any gin, trap, snare or similar device other than
												such as are mentioned in <ref id="ref34"
												href="#sec34-sub1-itma">paragraph (a)</ref>;</p>
										</item>
										<item id="sec34-sub1-itmb-itmvii">
											<num>(vii)</num>
											<p>any poison or like injurious substance, or any
												poisoned weapon;</p>
										</item>
										<item id="sec34-sub1-itmb-itmviii">
											<num>(viii)</num>
											<p>any other means or method of hunting which may be
												prescribed as unlawful;</p>
										</item>
									</list>
								</item>
								<item id="sec34-sub1-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>hunt any game animal during the period between seven o'clock
										in the evening and half-past five o'clock in the
									morning;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec34-sub1-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>partake in any game drive other than a drive of birds;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec34-sub1-itme">
									<num>(e)</num>
									<p>drive any game animal into water for the purpose of
										incapacitating, killing or capturing it.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec34-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who contravenes any of the provisions of <ref id="ref35"
									href="#sec34-sub1">subsection (1)</ref> shall be guilty of a
								forfeiture offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec34-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who is found away from his place of abode in possession of
								any of the things mentioned in paragraph (b) of subsection (1) in
								circumstances which, having regard in particular to the place in
								which he is so found and the place to or from which he is or appears
								to be travelling, raise a reasonable assumption that he has used, or
								intends or is about to use, such thing for hunting shall, unless he
								proves otherwise to the satisfaction of the court, be presumed to
								have such thing in his possession for the purpose of hunting an
								animal.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec35">
					<heading>Aircraft, motor vehicles, etc</heading>
					<subsection id="sec35-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>35.(1) No person shall approach in a motor vehicle Aircraft or
								aircraft to within five hundred metres of a game animal for the
								purpose of hunting that animal.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec35-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>No person shall use an aircraft or radio telephone for locating a
								game animal for the purpose of that animal being hunted or killed
								within forty-eight hours of such use.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec35-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>No person shall use any aircraft, motor vehicle or mechanically
								propelled vessel in such a manner as to drive, stampede or unduly
								disturb any protected animal or game animal for any purpose
								whatsoever: <eol/>Provided that this subsection shall not prohibit
								the use of an aircraft or radio telephone or vehicle-</p>
							<list id="sec35-sub3-lst1">
								<item id="sec35-sub3-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>for the purpose of driving any animal away from a recognized
										aerodrome or airfield or from any other area if necessary to
										enable an aircraft to land safely; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec35-sub3-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>for the purpose of driving any animal away from land for the
										time being under cultivation or in use for the grazing or
										herding of stock; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec35-sub3-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>for any other purpose which may be prescribed.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec35-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>No person shall discharge any firearm at or in the direction of any
								game animal from a motor vehicle or aircraft or from within four
								hundred metres of a motor vehicle.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec35-sub5">
						<num>(5)</num>
						<content>
							<p>No person shall shoot any game animal from a mechanically propelled
								vessel whilst the vessel is in mechanically induced motion.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec35-sub6">
						<num>(6)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who contravenes any of the provisions of this section
								shall be guilty of a forfeiture offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec36">
					<heading>Use of dogs</heading>
					<subsection id="sec36-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>36.(1) No person shall, without the written permission of a warden,
								which may be refused without any reason being assigned therefor, use
								dogs for the purpose of hunting any game animal.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec36-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who uses a dog in contravention of this section shall be
								guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding five
								thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding
								twelve months or to both and the court by which the person is
								convicted may also order the destruction of such dog.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec37">
					<heading>Power to prohibit use of certain weapons, etc</heading>
					<subsection id="sec37-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>37.(1) The Minister may, by notice in the Gazette, prohibit the
								hunting of any game animal, or may by such notice impose such
								conditions or restrictions in respect of the use of any specified
								means of hunting, weapon or missile as he may think fit.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec37-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who hunts any animal-</p>
							<list id="sec37-sub2-lst1">
								<item id="sec37-sub2-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>by any means, weapon or missile the use of which is
										prohibited under this section; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec37-sub2-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>in breach of any condition or restriction imposed in respect
										of the use of the means, weapon or missile used by him in
										such hunting, shall be guilty of a forfeiture offence.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec38">
					<heading>Close seasons</heading>
					<subsection id="sec38-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>38.(1) The Minister may, by notice in the Gazette, declare that,
								during such period and within such area as may be specified in the
								notice, the hunting of such game animals or game birds as may be so
								specified shall be unlawful.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec38-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who hunts any animal in contravention of a notice under
								this section shall be guilty of a forfeiture offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
			</part>
			<part id="prtV">
				<heading>PART V - TROPHIES AND LIVE ANIMALS</heading>
				<section id="sec39">
					<heading>Government trophies</heading>
					<subsection id="sec39-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>39.(1) Except as otherwise provided in this Act, the following shall
								be Government trophies and the property of the Government- </p>
							<list id="sec39-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec39-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>any trophy found without an owner;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec39-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>any protected animal, game animal or game bird found dead or
										killed by accident or mistake;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec39-sub1-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>any protected animal or game animal killed in defence of
										life, or in other circumstances authorized by or under this
										Act, by a person who is not the holder of a game licence
										authorizing him to hunt such animal;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec39-sub1-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>any animal or trophy in respect of which a breach of any of
										the provisions of this Act or the rules has been
									committed;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec39-sub1-itme">
									<num>(e)</num>
									<p>any animal killed by an officer of the Service in the course
										of his duties as such;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec39-sub1-itmf">
									<num>(f)</num>
									<p>the meat of any animal mentioned in this subsection.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec39-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who by any means obtains possession of a Government trophy
								shall forthwith make a report thereof to an authorized officer and
								shall hand the trophy over to the authorized officer.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec39-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who-</p>
							<list id="sec39-sub3-lst1">
								<item id="sec39-sub3-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>fails to make a report required by <ref id="ref36"
											href="#sec39-sub2">subsection (2)</ref>; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec39-sub3-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>is unlawfully in possession of, or unlawfully deals in, any
										Government trophy, shall be guilty of an offence and liable
										to a fine not exceeding ten thousand shillings or to
										imprisonment for a term not exceeding twelve months or to
										both.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec39-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>In any proceedings against any person for an offence against this
								section, the onus of proving that any possession or dealing was
								lawful shall be upon that person.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec40">
					<heading>Importation of trophies</heading>
					<subsection id="sec40-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>40. (1) After the appointed day no person shall import any trophy, or
								any unmanufactured ivory or rhinoceros horn of any description,
								unless it is imported through a customs port of entry and produced
								at the time of importation to a proper officer of customs:
								<eol/>Provided that no person shall, without the written permission
								of the Minister, import any trophy of a class which the Minister, by
								notice in the Gazette, has declared to be a prohibited import.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec40-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>An officer of customs to whom any trophy, ivory or horn is produced
								under <ref id="ref37" href="#sec40-sub1">subsection (1)</ref> shall
								issue to the person by whom it is produced an acknowledgement of
								production in the prescribed form, and shall forthwith send a copy
								of the acknowledgement to the Director.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec40-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Within fourteen days after any importation under this section, the
								importer shall produce the trophy, ivory or horn concerned, together
								with the acknowledgement of production issued under <ref id="ref38"
									href="#sec40-sub2">subsection (2)</ref>, to the Director who
								shall weigh, mark and register the trophy, ivory or horn in such
								manner, if any, as may be prescribed and shall, unless the importer
								is in possession of a certificate of ownership or equivalent
								document issued by a competent authority of the country of origin of
								the trophy, ivory or horn, and subject to <ref id="ref39"
									href="#sec40-sub4">subsection (4)</ref>, issue a certificate of
								ownership in respect thereof.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec40-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>A certificate of ownership shall not be issued under <ref id="ref40"
									href="#sec40-sub3">subsection (3)</ref> in respect of any
								trophy, ivory or rhinoceros horn imported directly from any country
								to which this subsection has been applied by the Minister by notice
								in the Gazette unless the Director is satisfied that such trophy,
								ivory or horn has been lawfully exported from that country.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec40-sub5">
						<num>(5)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who-</p>
							<list id="sec40-sub5-lst1">
								<item id="sec40-sub5-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>imports or attempts to import any trophy, ivory or rhinoceros
										horn in contravention of <ref id="ref42" href="#sec40-sub1"
											>subsection (1)</ref>; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec40-sub5-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>fails to produce any trophy, ivory or rhinoceros horn as
										required by <ref id="ref41" href="#sec40-sub3">subsection
											(3)</ref>, shall be guilty of a forfeiture offence and
										liable to a fine not exceeding ten thousand shillings or to
										imprisonment for a term not exceeding three years or to
										both. .</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec41">
					<heading>Certificates of ownership relating to hunted animals</heading>
					<subsection id="sec41-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>41.(1) Where any person kills or captures any animal under the
								authorization of a game licence, he shall, within thirty days after
								the killing or capture, produce the animal or, as the case may be,
								any trophy of the animal which he wishes to retain, to a warden who
								shall issue a certificate of ownership in respect thereof:
								<eol/>Provided that, if the person wishes to have any process
								applied in Kenya to the trophy, a warden may, upon application made
								to him in that behalf, extend the period of thirty days for such
								further period as he may consider necessary to enable the processing
								to be carried out before the issue of a certificate of ownership in
								respect of the completed trophy.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec41-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who fails to produce any animal or trophy as required by
								this section shall be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not
								exceeding ten thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a term not
								exceeding three years or to both: <eol/>Provided that it shall be a
								defence to any proceedings under this subsection for the accused to
								prove to the satisfaction of the court that his failure to comply
								with the provisions of <ref id="ref43" href="#sec41-sub1">subsection
									(1)</ref> arose from circumstances beyond his control and that
								he produced the animal or trophy concerned to a warden at the
								earliest practicable time.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec42">
					<heading>Certificates of ownership for possession of trophies</heading>
					<subsection id="sec42-sub1">
						<sidenote>16 of 1977, Sch.  </sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>42.(1) Except as otherwise provided by this Act, any person who is in
								possession of any trophy, or of any ivory or rhinoceros horn of any
								description, without also being in possession of a certificate of
								ownership in respect thereof shall be guilty of a forfeiture offence
								and- </p>
							<list id="sec42-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec42-sub1-itma">
									<p>(a) if that person is the holder of a dealer's licence under
											<ref id="ref44" href="#sec43">section 43</ref>, be
										liable to a fine not exceeding thirty thousand shillings or
										to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years or to
										both; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec42-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>in any other case, be liable to a fine not exceeding ten
										thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a term not
										exceeding three years or to both.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec42-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>This section shall not apply to the possession of a trophy by any
								person who has the possession solely by reason of being a receiver
								or trustee in bankruptcy or the personal representative of a
								deceased person.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec42-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>In this section and in <ref id="ref45" href="#sec44">sections 44 and
									45</ref> "certificate of ownership" means-</p>
							<list id="sec42-sub3-lst1">
								<item id="sec42-sub3-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>a certificate of ownership issued under any of the provisions
										of this Act;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec42-sub3-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>a certificate of ownership issued under any former law
										relating to wildlife; and</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec42-sub3-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>a certificate of ownership or equivalent documents issued by
										a competent officer or other authority of the country of
										origin of the trophy concerned.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec43">
					<heading>Dealers</heading>
					<subsection id="sec43-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>43.(1) No person shall carry on the business of a dealer unless he is
								the holder of a valid dealer's licence issued by a licensing
								officer.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec43-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>An application for a dealer's licence shall be made to a licensing
								officer in the prescribed form, and the licensing officer may grant
								or, without assigning any reason therefor, refuse to grant the
								licence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec43-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>A dealer's licence-</p>
							<list id="sec43-sub3-lst1">
								<item id="sec43-sub3-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>shall be in the prescribed form;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec43-sub3-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>shall be subject to such conditions as may be prescribed or
										authorized by the rules regulating the manner, place or
										hours in, at or during which the licensed business may be
										carried on and the trophies or class of trophies which may
										be dealt in;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec43-sub3-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>shall be subject to the payment of the prescribed fee, and
										different fees may be prescribed for different classes of
										dealers;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec43-sub3-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>shall, subject to any other provision of this Act, be valid
										for a period of twelve months from the date of issue
										thereof.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec43-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who-</p>
							<list id="sec43-sub4-lst1">
								<item id="sec43-sub4-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>not being the holder of a dealer's licence, carries on the
										business of a dealer; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec43-sub4-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>being the holder of a dealer's licence, fails to comply with
										any condition to which the licence is subject,</p>
								</item>
							</list>
							<p>shall be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding
								twenty thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a term not
								exceeding five years or to both.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec44">
					<heading>Transfer of trophies</heading>
					<subsection id="sec44-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>44.(1) Subject to <ref id="ref46" href="#sec44-sub3">subsection
								(3)</ref>, no person shall transfer the ownership of any trophy to
								any other person by way of gift, sale or otherwise unless he is in
								possession of a certificate of ownership in respect of the trophy
								and unless, at the time of the transfer, he endorses the certificate
								with the date of transfer and the name of the person to whom the
								trophy is transferred and hands over the certificate to that other
								person.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec44-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who transfers any trophy to another otherwise than in
								compliance with subsection (1) shall be guilty of an offence and
								liable to a fine not exceeding ten thousand shillings or to
								imprisonment for a term not exceeding twelve months or to both.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec44-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Nothing in this section shall apply to any transfer of ownership of a
								trophy by operation of law or in consequence of the death of the
								owner of the trophy.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec45">
					<heading>Export of trophies etc</heading>
					<subsection id="sec45-sub1">
						<sidenote>11 of 1983, Sch.</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>45.(1) No person shall export any live protected animal, of game
								animal or game bird except-</p>
							<list id="sec45-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec45-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>through a customs port of entry; and</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec45-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>under and in accordance with an export permit issued by the
										Director on payment of the prescribed fee, which shall be
										non-refundable whether or not the permit is granted, and
										which permit may be refused by the Director without
										assigning any reason therefor.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec45-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>No person shall export any trophy other than a live animal except
								through a customs port of entry and upon production to a proper
								officer of customs of a certificate of ownership relating to that
								trophy.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec45-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Notwithstanding <ref id="ref47" href="#sec45-sub1">subsections (1)
									and (2)</ref> no person shall, without the written permission of
								the Minister, export any animal or trophy of a class which the
								Minister, by notice in the Gazette, has declared to be a prohibited
								export.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec45-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Nothing in this section shall apply to any animal or trophy which is-</p>
							<list id="sec45-sub4-lst1">
								<item id="sec45-sub4-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>in transit through Kenya if the animal or trophy is
										accompanied by the necessary transit documents issued in the
										country of origin or export and is entered through a customs
										port of entry; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec45-sub4-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>accompanied by a person who is in possession of, and produces
										to a proper officer of customs, a certificate issued in
										Tanzania or Uganda certifying that such person is lawfully
										authorized to export, the animal or trophy, and the person
										satisfies the officer of customs that-</p>
									<list id="sec45-sub4-itmb-lst1">
										<item id="sec45-sub4-itmb-itmi">
											<num>(i)</num>
											<p>the certificate was issued to him; and</p>
										</item>
										<item id="sec45-sub4-itmb-itmii">
											<num>(ii)</num>
											<p>that he is himself exporting the animal or trophy
												from Kenya.</p>
										</item>
									</list>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec45-sub5">
						<num>(5)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who exports or attempts to export any animal or trophy in
								contravention of any of the provisions of this section shall be
								guilty of a forfeiture offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec46">
					<heading>Exemptions</heading>
					<subsection id="sec46-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>46.The Minister may, by notice in the Gazette, exempt any class of
								trophy from all or any of the provisions of this part.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec47">
					<heading>Game meat</heading>
					<subsection id="sec47-sub47">
						<content>
							<p>47.(1) The Minister may, by regulation, prohibit, control or regulate
								the possession or movement of, or any dealings of any nature
								whatsoever in, any meat.Export of trophies, etc.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec47-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Without prejudice to the generality of subsection (1), regulations
								thereunder may-</p>
							<list id="sec47-sub2-lst1">
								<item id="sec47-sub2-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>provide for the licensing of persons and premises;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec47-sub2-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>provide for the inspection of premises other than
										dwelling-houses;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec47-sub2-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>specify the conditions upon which game-ranching and game
										cropping may be undertaken, and provide for the exemption of
										game-ranching and game cropping from the provisions of this
										Act relating to game or other licences;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec47-sub2-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>prescribe the fees to be payable in respect of any licence,
										permit or authorization issued or given thereunder;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec47-sub2-itme">
									<num>(e)</num>
									<p>impose penalties, in respect of any breach of the
										regulations, not exceeding a fine of twenty thousand
										shillings or imprisonment for a term not exceeding three
										years or both;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec47-sub2-itmf">
									<num>(f)</num>
									<p>provide for the forfeiture of any meat in respect of which
										any breach of the regulations occurs.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec48">
					<heading>Permit to keep live animals</heading>
					<subsection id="sec48-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>48.(1) No person shall keep in captivity any live protected animal,
								game animal or game bird except in accordance with a permit issued
								by a licensing officer in that behalf.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec48-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>A permit under this section-</p>
							<list id="sec48-sub2-lst1">
								<item id="sec48-sub2-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>shall be in addition to any certificate of ownership required
										under this Act;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec48-sub2-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>shall be issued, upon application, by the licensing officer
										unless he has reason to believe that the applicant is not a
										proper person to keep the animal when the licensing officer
										may refer the matter to the Director who may direct the
										licensing officer to issue or refuse the permit, and the
										decision of the Director thereon shall be final.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec48-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any animal or birds kept under the authority of a permit under this
								section shall be made available for inspection, together with the
								cage or other enclosure in which it is normally kept, by any warden
								at all reasonable times.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec48-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>If, upon an inspection made under this section, a warden is satisfied
								that the animal or bird concerned is not being adequately cared for,
								or that the conditions under which it is kept are not reasonably
								healthy or humane, the warden shall report the facts to the Director
								who may thereupon cancel the permit concerned and confiscate the
								animal or bird concerned which shall become the property of the
								Government.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec48-sub5">
						<num>(5)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who keeps any animal or bird in contravention of <ref
									id="ref48" href="#sec48-sub1">subsection (1)</ref>, or fails to
								make an animal, bird, cage or enclosure available for inspection as
								required by <ref id="ref49" href="#sec48-sub3">subsection (3)</ref>,
								shall be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding
								five thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding
								six months or to both.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec49">
					<heading>Powers of office.</heading>
					<subsection id="sec49-sub1">
						<sidenote>16 of 1989, s.6</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>49.(1) An authorized officer may stop and detain any person whom he
								finds doing any act for which a licence or permit is required under
								this Act or the rules for the purpose of requiring that person to
								produce his licence or permit, and if that person fails to produce
								the appropriate licence or permit he may be arrested by the officer
								without a warrant.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec49-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>If an authorized officer has reasonable grounds for believing that
								any person has committed an offence under this Act or the rules he
								may-</p>
							<list id="sec49-sub2-lst1">
								<item id="sec49-sub2-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>require the person to produce for inspection-</p>
									<list id="sec49-sub2-itma-lst1">
										<item id="sec49-sub2-itma-itmi">
											<num>(i)</num>
											<p>any animal, or any meat or other part of an animal,
												in his possession;</p>
										</item>
										<item id="sec49-sub2-itma-itmii">
											<num>(ii)</num>
											<p>any firearm or other weapon, trap, net or poison, or
												any instrument, material or thing, in relation to or
												in connexion with which any offence appears to the
												officer to have been committed;</p>
										</item>
										<item id="sec49-sub2-itma-itmiii">
											<num>(iii)</num>
											<p>any licence, permit or other document required to be
												had or be kept by such person under the provisions
												of this Act or the rules;</p>
										</item>
									</list>
								</item>
								<item id="sec49-sub2-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>enter and search, with or without assistance, any land,
										building, tent, vehicle or boat in the occupation or
										possession of such person, and open and search any baggage
										or other thing in the possession of such person: Provided
										that no dwelling-house shall be entered without a warrant
										except under exceptional circumstances;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec49-sub2-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>seize and detain anything which appears to the officer to be
										a Government trophy, or any vehicle, boat, firearm or other
										weapon, trap, net or poison, or any instrument, material or
										thing whatsoever in relation to or in connexion with which
										any offence against his Act or the rules appears to have
										been committed or which appears to the officer to have been
										used in, or for the purposes of, the commission of any such
										offence, whether or not it is in the immediate possession of
										any person;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec49-sub2-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>arrest and detain such person if he has reason to believe
										that such person will not appear and answer any charge which
										may be preferred against him.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec49-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>For the purpose of the more effective enforcement of the provisions
								of this Act, a senior officer, or a subordinate officer authorized
								by him in that behalf, may erect a temporary barrier across any road
								or place and any person approaching the barrier shall, on being
								required by the officer so to do, stop and allow the officer to
								carry out such search of his own person and of any vehicle as may
								appear to the officer to be necessary or expedient.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec49-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who-</p>
							<list id="sec49-sub4-lst1">
								<item id="sec49-sub4-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>without reasonable excuse, fails to produce anything which,
										under the powers conferred by this section, he is required
										to produce; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec49-sub4-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>fails to stop or to allow a search when so required under
										subsection(3); or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec49-sub4-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>assaults, resists or wilfully obstructs any officer in the
										exercise of the powers conferred upon such officer by this
										section,</p>
								</item>
							</list>
							<p>shall be guilty of an offence and liable to a fine not exceeding ten
								thousand shillings or to imprisonment for a period not exceeding
								twelve months or to both. </p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec49-sub5">
						<num>(5)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Neither the Government nor any officer shall be responsible for any
								loss or damage which may occur to any property during an act of
								seizure, or whilst such property is detained, under this section,
								unless the same has been caused maliciously or fraudulently or by
								gross neglect.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec50">
					<heading>Disposal of persons arrested and things seized.</heading>
					<subsection id="sec50-sub1">
						<sidenote>16 of 1989, s.7.</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>50. (1) Any person arrested under section 49 shall forth with be
								taken before a court to be dealt with according to law.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec50-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Where anything other than a trophy is seized and detained under
								section 49 of this Act it shall be forfeited to the Government after
								a period of three months unless within that period some person is
								charged with a forfeiture offence under the Act and it is alleged
								that-</p>
							<list id="sec50-sub2-lst1">
								<item id="sec50-sub2-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>the offence was committed in relation to or in connection
										with that thing; or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec50-sub2-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>the thing was used in, or for the purpose of, the commission
										of such an offence.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec50-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Notwithstanding subsection (2)-</p>
							<list id="sec50-sub3-lst1">
								<item id="sec50-sub3-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>where anything seized and detained under section 49 is
										subject to speedy and natural decay, and it is not
										reasonably practicable to take effective steps to preserve
										the same, the officer by whom the same is seized or an
										officer to whose orders he is subject may, without obtaining
										any order from a court, destroy or otherwise dispose of that
										thing if he considers it desirable so to do;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec50-sub3-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>where any apparently unlawful means of hunting cannot
										practicably be removed from its location it may forthwith be
										rendered inoperative;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec50-sub3-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>where any apparently unlawful means of hunting cannot
										practicably be removed from its location it may forthwith be
										rendered inoperative.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec51">
					<heading>Effect of conviction and powers of court</heading>
					<subsection id="sec51-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>51.(1) Where the holder of a licence, permit, permission or
								authorization granted or issued under this Act or the rules is
								convicted of an offence under this Act the conviction shall, unless
								the court otherwise directs for reasons to be recorded in writing,
								have the effect of cancelling the licence, permit, permission or
								authorization with effect from the date of conviction.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec51-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The holder of a licence, permit, permission or authorization which is
								cancelled under <ref id="ref63" href="#sec51-sub1">subsection
								(1)</ref> shall, within fourteen days from the date of conviction,
								surrender to the court the licence or permit, or any document
								evidencing the permission or authorization, and any person who fails
								to comply with the provisions of this subsection shall be guilty of
								an offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec51-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Where any person is convicted of an offence under this Act or the
								rules in respect of any game-pit, pitfall, trench or similar
								excavation, or any fence or enclosure, or any other device
								whatsoever fixed to the ground, which such person has unlawfully
								made, used or had in his possession for the purpose of hunting, the
								court may, in addition to any other punishment, order that such
								game-pit, pitfall, trench, excavation, fence, enclosure or device
								shall be destroyed or obliterated by the Service in such manner as
								the court may specify, and any expenditure incurred on account of
								such order shall be a civil debt recoverable summarily from such
								person by the Government.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec51-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>A court before which a person is convicted of an offence against this
								Act or the rules shall forthwith make a report in the prescribed
								form to the Director containing the details of the offence and the
								sentence and particulars of any other order made by the court in
								relation to the conviction.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec52">
					<heading>Forfeiture.</heading>
					<subsection id="sec52-sub1">
						<sidenote>16 of 1989, s.8.</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>52. (1) Where a person is convicted of a forfeiture offence the court
								shall, unless it considers, for reasons to be recorded by the court,
								that in all the circumstances of the case it would be unjust so to
								do, order that any animal, trophy, weapon, net, vehicle, instrument,
								material or thing whatsoever, whether similar to those enumerated or
								not, in relation to, in connexion with, or by means of which the
								offence has been committed shall be forfeited to the Government.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec52-sub2">
						<content>
							<p>(2) Where anything other than a Government trophy has been seized and
								detained under <ref id="ref56" href="#sec49">section 49</ref> of
								this Act and a person charged with forfeiture offence in relation
								thereto within three months of the seizure has not appeared to
								answer the charge the thing shall be forfeited to the
							Government.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec52-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Where anything other than a Government trophy has been seized and
								detained under section 49 of this Act and a person charged with
								forfeiture offence in relation thereto within three months of the
								seizure has not appeared to answer the charge the thing shall be
								forfeited to the Government.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec53">
					<heading>Ineligibility to hold licences, etc</heading>
					<subsection id="sec53-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>53. Except as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, any person
								who is convicted of an offence under this Act or the rules, or under
								any law relating to the preservation of wild game for the time being
								in force in Tanzania or Uganda, shall be disqualified from holding a
								licence or permit under this Act or the rules for a period of three
								years from the date of the conviction:<eol/>Provided that the
								Minister may, in any particular case, direct that this section shall
								not apply or that the period of disqualification shall be
							reduced.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec54">
					<heading>Conduct of prosecutions.</heading>
					<subsection id="sec54-sub1">
						<sidenote>Cap. 75.</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>54. Any warden may, subject to the directions of the
								Attorney-General, conduct any prosecution for an offence under this
								Act or the rules, and shall for that purpose have all the powers
								conferred upon a public prosecutor by the Criminal Procedure
							Code.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec55">
					<heading>Exemption of officers of the Service</heading>
					<subsection id="sec55-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>55. Nothing in this Act shall be constructed as rendering an officer
								of the Service guilty of an offence under this Act or the rules in
								respect of anything done by him in the course of his duty as such
								officer, but where the officer is charged with such an offence the
								onus of proving that anything done by him was done in the course of
								his duty shall lie upon him.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec56">
					<heading>General penalties</heading>
					<subsection id="sec56-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>56. (1) Any person who is guilty of an offence under this Act for
								which no other penalty is expressly provided shall be liable- </p>
							<list id="sec56-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec56-sub1-itma">
									<p>(a) if the offence is committed in respect of a protected
										animal or an animal mentioned in Part I of the First
										Schedule, or in respect of any trophy of that animal, to a
										fine not exceeding forty thousand shillings or to
										imprisonment for a term not exceeding ten years or to
									both;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec56-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>if the offence is committed in respect of an animal mentioned
										in Part II of the First Schedule, or in respect of any
										trophy of that animal, to a fine not exceeding twenty
										thousand shillings or to imprisonment of a term not
										exceeding five years or to both;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec56-sub1-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>if the offence is a forfeiture offence not included in <ref
											id="ref57" href="#sec56-sub1-itma">paragraph (a)</ref>
										or <ref id="ref58" href="#sec56-sub1-itmb">(b)</ref>, to a
										fine not exceeding fifteen thousand shillings or to
										imprisonment for a term not exceeding three years or to
										both;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec56-sub1-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>in any other case, to a fine not exceeding two thousand
										shillings or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six
										months or to both.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec56-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Upon the conviction of any person for an offence under this Act which
								relates to more than one animal or trophy the court may inflict an
								additional punishment in respect of each animal or trophy after the
								first of a fine not exceeding six thousand shillings, or one-half of
								the fine prescribed by this Act for the offence, whichever is the
								less.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec57">
					<heading>Corporations and firms</heading>
					<subsection id="sec57-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>57. (1) Where a corporation is guilty of an offence under this Act or
								the rules, every director, secretary or officer of the corporation
								shall, unless he proves that the offence was committed without his
								knowledge or consent, also be liable to be prosecuted, tried,
								convicted and punished for that offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec57-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Where any firm or individual has, in the course of business,
								committed any offence under this Act or the rules then, without
								prejudice to the liability of the firm or individual for the
								offence, every manager or other person concerned in the management
								of such business shall, unless he proves that the offence was
								committed without his knowledge or consent, also be liable to be
								prosecuted, tried, convicted and punished for that offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec58">
					<num>58.</num>
					<heading>Title of section 58</heading>
					<subsection id="sec58-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>Original text of section 58.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec59">
					<num>59.</num>
					<heading>Title of Section 59.</heading>
					<subsection id="sec59-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>Original text of section 59.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec60">
					<num>60.</num>
					<heading>Title of Section 60</heading>
					<subsection id="sec60-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>Original text of Section 60.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec61">
					<heading>Unlawful possession of Service property, etc</heading>
					<subsection id="sec61-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>61. (1) Any person who, not being a member of the Service, is in
								possession of an article which has been supplied to any such officer
								for use in the execution of his duties as such, and who fails to
								account satisfactorily for such possession shall be guilty of an
								offence.<eol/>(2) Any person who, without lawful authority <eol/>(a)
								purchases or receives any article which has been supplied to a
								member of the Service for use in the execution of his duties as
								such; <eol/>(b) aids or abets a member of the Service in selling or
								disposing of any such article; <eol/>(c) assumes the uniform or any
								distinctive part thereof, of, or otherwise pretends to act as or to
								personate, any officer of the Service shall be guilty of an
							offence.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec62">
					<heading>Compensation for personal injury or death.</heading>
					<subsection id="sec62-sub1">
						<sidenote>16 of 1989, s.11.</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>62. Where any person suffers any bodily injury from or is killed by
								any animal, the person injured or in the case of a deceased person,
								any other person who was dependant upon him at the date of his
								death, may make application to a district committee established by
								this section, for the award of compensation for the injury or death:
								<eol/>Provided that no compensation shall be claimable where the
								injury or death occurred- </p>
							<list id="sec62-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec62-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>in the course of any conduct on the part of the person
										concerned which would constitute an offence under this Act;
										or</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec62-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>in the course of normal wildlife utilization activities.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec62-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>For the purposes of receiving and considering applications under <ref
									id="ref53" href="#sec62-sub1">subsection (1)</ref>, and of
								awarding compensation thereunder, there is hereby established in
								each district a committee which shall consist of-</p>
							<list id="sec62-sub2-lst1">
								<item id="sec62-sub2-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>the District Commissioner, who shall be the chairman of the
										committee;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec62-sub2-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>the Divisional Officer of the Service;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec62-sub2-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>the Officer in Charge of the Police Division;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec62-sub2-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>the District Medical Officer;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec62-sub2-itme">
									<num>(e)</num>
									<p>one Elected Member of the National Assembly representing a
										constituency in the district, who shall be appointed by the
										Minister;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec62-sub2-itmf">
									<num>(f)</num>
									<p>the chairman of County Council in the district; and</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec62-sub2-itmg">
									<num>(g)</num>
									<p>three other members appointed by the Minister to represent
										the general public of the district.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec62-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>A District Committee may co-opt any person whom it considers may
								assist it either generally or for the consideration of any
								particular case.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec62-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Compensation awarded under this section shall be payable out of
								moneys provided by Parliament for that purpose.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec63">
					<heading>Land use</heading>
					<subsection id="sec63-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>63. Where any written law, or any document of title to any land,
								makes a reference to improvements to such land, or to principles of
								good husbandry, or any like reference which relates to livestock,
								such reference shall be deemed to include any game-ranching, game
								cropping or other wildlife utilization lawfully undertaken under the
								rules.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec64">
					<heading>Application of Act to non-game animals</heading>
					<subsection id="sec64-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>64. The Minister may, by notice in the Gazette, declare that any
								provision of this Act shall apply to any animal not mentioned in a
								schedule, or to any trophy or meat of any such animal, and upon
								publication of such notice the animal concerned shall be deemed to
								be a game animal or game bird for the purposes of such
							provision.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec65">
					<heading>Appeal to Tribunal</heading>
					<subsection id="sec65-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>65. (1) There is hereby established an Appeal Tribunal which shall be
								known as the Wildlife Conservation and Management Service Appeal
								Tribunal.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec65-sub2">
						<num>(2)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The Tribunal shall consider and determine appeals from any decision
								in any matter, wherein any person is aggrieved by a refusal of the
								grant or issue of, or by any condition other than a prescribed
								condition attached to, or the cancellation or suspension of, any
								licence, permit or authorization under this Act.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec65-sub3">
						<num>(3)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who is dissatisfied with the manner in which compensation
								is made or not made under <ref id="ref60" href="#sec62">section
								62</ref> may appeal to the Tribunal within the time prescribed by
								regulations made under <ref id="ref54" href="#sec67-sub1-itmg"
									>section 67(g)</ref>.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec65-sub4">
						<num>(4)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Appeals to the Tribunal under this Act shall be made within thirty
								days of the date of the decision appealed against.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec65-sub5">
						<num>(5)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The Tribunal shall consist of-</p>
							<list id="sec65-sub5-lst1">
								<item id="sec65-sub5-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>the chairman appointed by the Minister; and</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec65-sub5-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>not less than two and not more than five other members
										appointed by the Minister of whom one shall be appointed for
										his knowledge of wildlife management and conservation.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec65-sub6">
						<num>(6)</num>
						<content>
							<p>There shall be an assessor to the Tribunal who shall be an advocate
								of not less than five years standing appointed by the Tribunal with
								the approval of the Minister and the assessor, when the Tribunal so
								requires, shall attend the proceedings of the Tribunal and advise it
								on questions of law.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec65-sub7">
						<num>(7)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The Minister shall appoint a public officer to be secretary to the
								Tribunal.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec65-sub8">
						<num>(8)</num>
						<content>
							<p>For the purposes of hearing and determining the appeals, by the
								Tribunal-</p>
							<list id="sec65-sub8-lst1">
								<item id="sec65-sub8-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>the chairman or other person presiding may administer
									oaths;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec65-sub8-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>the chairman may, by notice under his hand, summon any person
										to attend and give evidence and to produce any relevant
										document.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec65-sub9">
						<num>(9)</num>
						<content>
							<p>The cost of the appeal shall be in the discretion of the <ref
									id="ref65" href="/ke/act/1975-12-12/23/schedule.1"
								>Tribunal</ref>, which may make such order as to costs as appear to
								it just; and any such costs shall be recoverable as a civil
							debt.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
					<subsection id="sec65-sub10">
						<num>(10)</num>
						<content>
							<p>Any person who, after payment or tender to him of his reasonable
								expenses, without reasonable excuse fails, when summoned by the
								Tribunal, to attend and give evidence or produce any document which
								he is required to produce shall be guilty of an offence and liable
								to a fine not exceeding five thousand shillings or to imprisonment
								for a term not exceeding six months or to both.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec66">
					<heading>Duplicate licences</heading>
					<subsection id="sec66-sub1">
						<content>
							<p>66. Where any licence, permit or authorization granted or issued
								under this Act or the rules has been lost or destroyed the person to
								whom it was granted or issued may apply to the officer by whom it
								was issued for a duplicate thereof which may be issued at the
								discretion of that officer upon payment of the prescribed fee.</p>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
				<section id="sec67">
					<heading>Power to make regulations</heading>
					<subsection id="sec67-sub1">
						<sidenote>2 of 2002, Sch.</sidenote>
						<content>
							<p>67. The Minister may make regulations for the better carrying into
								effect of the provisions of this Act, and, without prejudice to the
								generality of such powers, the regulations may- </p>
							<list id="sec67-sub1-lst1">
								<item id="sec67-sub1-itma">
									<num>(a)</num>
									<p>specify the conditions subject to which any licence, permit
										or authorization may be granted or issued under this
									Act;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec67-sub1-itmb">
									<num>(b)</num>
									<p>prescribe the procedure to be followed in respect of an
										application for the licence, permit or authorization;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec67-sub1-itmc">
									<num>(c)</num>
									<p>classify game licences and specify the animals which may be
										included in any game licence, and the numbers thereof which
										may be hunted under that licence;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec67-sub1-itmd">
									<num>(d)</num>
									<p>limit the number of game licences which may be issued to any
										person or in respect of any specified period or area;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec67-sub1-itme">
									<num>(e)</num>
									<p>prohibit the use of any specified type or calibre of weapon
										in the hunting of any specified type of game animal or game
										bird;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec67-sub1-itmf">
									<num>(f)</num>
									<p>restrict, regulate or otherwise control the supply of
										trophies to dealers;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec67-sub1-itmg">
									<num>(g)</num>
									<p>make provision for the manner and time in which applications
										for the award of compensation under <ref id="ref62"
											href="#sec62">section 62</ref> may be made, for
										prescribing the level of such compensation and for the
										regulation of the proceedings of District Committees
										established under that section and the Appeal Tribunal
										established under <ref id="ref61" href="#sec65">section
										65</ref> and the manner and time within which appeals under
											<ref id="ref55" href="#sec65-sub3">section 65(3)</ref>
										may be made;</p>
								</item>
								<item id="sec67-sub1-itmh">
									<num>(h)</num>
									<p>make provision for the training of personnel for the
									service.</p>
								</item>
							</list>
						</content>
					</subsection>
				</section>
			</part>
		</body>
	</act>
</akomantoso>
